<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Maarten Goos</title>
    <link>/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Maarten Goos</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 14 Sep 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Graduate Labour Economics</title>
      <link>/teaching/c2/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Sep 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/teaching/c2/</guid>
      <description>This graduate course in labour economics presents an in-depth overview of recent research in labour economics focussing on inequality, technological change, globalization, worker power, and monopsony. The course stresses the most recent theories as well as recent advances in empirical research designs.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Undergraduate Labour Economics</title>
      <link>/teaching/c1/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Sep 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/teaching/c1/</guid>
      <description>This undergraduate course presents an introduction into the field of labour economics. It stresses the ideas that labour economists use to understand how the labour market works. The course also introduces empirical strategies to test these ideas with data, and discusses evidence obtained from landmark research studies in labour economics.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Impact of AI on Work</title>
      <link>/more/m2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/more/m2/</guid>
      <description>This article summarizes the economic literature on the impact of AI on work.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What Happens to Workers at Firms that Automate</title>
      <link>/research/12/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/research/12/</guid>
      <description>This paper estimates the impact of firm-level investments in automation technologies on worker-level outcomes. It finds that automation increases the probability of incumbent workers separating from their employers, in line with recent task-based models of automation. It shows that incumbent workers experience a 5-year cumulative wage income loss of 9 percent of one year&amp;rsquo;s earnings on average, driven by decreases in days worked. These adverse impacts of automation are larger in smaller firms, and for older and less-educated workers. By contrast, no such losses are found for firms&amp;rsquo; investments in computers.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Future of Work</title>
      <link>/more/m1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/more/m1/</guid>
      <description>The Future of Work</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Routine-Biased Technical Change: Firm-Level Evidence from a Plant Closure</title>
      <link>/research/11/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/research/11/</guid>
      <description>This paper uses unique survey data of workers at a large car plant who became unemployed when the plant closed. In line with the RBTC hypothesis, it finds that re-employment probabilities 1,5 years after the plant’s closure are substantially higher for workers with nonroutine task competencies and with digital skills. Moreover, for the subset of individuals who were re-employed 1,5 years after the plant’s closure, the paper finds that the nonroutine content of job tasks is higher, wages are lower, and contracts are less permanent.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Firm-Level Automation: Evidence from The Netherlands</title>
      <link>/research/10/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/research/10/</guid>
      <description>This paper uses a Dutch firm-level survey on automation expenditures linked to administrative records covering the universe of firms in the Netherlands to consider firm-level automation over 2000–2016. It shows that net employment at firms falls after investments in automation technology. Importantly, this effect arises among both manufacturing and nonmanufacturing firms, indicating that this is not specific to technologies like robotics.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Markets for Jobs and their Task Overlap</title>
      <link>/research/9/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/research/9/</guid>
      <description>This paper shows that the labour market is organized along jobs and their task content. It shows that tightness in markets for jobs for which an unemployed job seeker fully qualifies in terms of her task competencies is predictive of her unemployment duration. The paper also finds that unemployed job seekers do not compete in markets where they possess only part of the required task competencies, suggesting that task overlap across jobs is unimportant for worker mobility between job markets.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Job Polarization: An Historical Perspective</title>
      <link>/research/8/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Jul 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/research/8/</guid>
      <description>This paper uses historical labour market data for Belgium for the period 1846–2011 to illustrate how the employment impacts of the ongoing Digital Revolution after 1980 compare to those of the Second Industrial Revolution before 1980. In particular, it shows that labour markets after 1980 are not uniquely characterized by exceptionally high labour market turbulence but by the nature of changes in the composition of jobs, namely a process of job polarization.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Local High-Tech Job Multipliers in Europe</title>
      <link>/research/7/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/research/7/</guid>
      <description>This article finds that each worker in a high-skilled occupation creates up to five extra jobs in local less-skilled-intensive services in the same region. However, it is also shown that there exist persistent differences in the size of this local high-tech job multiplier across regions.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Measuring Teaching Quality in Higher Education: Assessing Selection Bias in Course Evaluations</title>
      <link>/research/6/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Feb 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/research/6/</guid>
      <description>This paper finds that there is an upward selection bias in students&amp;rsquo; course evaluations, and that correcting for this bias has non-negligible effects on the average evaluation score and on the evaluation-based ranking of courses. However, we find that adjusting for selection only has small impacts on the measured effects of observables on course evaluations, validating a large related literature which considers the observable determinants of evaluation scores without correcting for selection bias.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Explaining Job Polarization in Europe: Routine-Biased Technological Change and Offshoring</title>
      <link>/research/5/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Aug 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/research/5/</guid>
      <description>This paper documents the pervasiveness of job polarization in 16 Western European countries over the period 1993–2010. It then develops and estimates a framework to explain job polarization using routine-biased technological change and offshoring. This model can explain much of both total job polarization and the split into within-industry and between-industry components.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Platform Pricing in Matching Markets</title>
      <link>/research/4/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Feb 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/research/4/</guid>
      <description>This paper introduces matching in two-sided markets. It shows that a platform&amp;rsquo;s positive cross-side and negative own-side network externalities can be summarized by a general matching function that captures the efficiency of the platform&amp;rsquo;s matching technology. The paper also shows that the pricing strategy of a monopoly matchmaker only partially internalizes the efficiency of its matching technology.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Job Polarization in Europe</title>
      <link>/research/3/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 May 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/research/3/</guid>
      <description>This paper documents the pervasiveness of job polarization across 16 European countries. It also discusses several hypotheses about the reasons for job polarization. First, the “routinization” hypothesis (first put forward by Autor, Levy, and Murnane 2003) suggests that technological progress is to replace “routine” labor which tends to be clerical and craft jobs in the middle of the wage distribution. Second, there is the view that globalization is an important source of change in the job structure in the richest countries. Third, the rise in the share of income going to the rich may have led to an increase in demand for low-skill workers whose employment increasingly consists of providing services to the rich.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Lousy and Lovely Jobs: The Rising Polarization of Work in Britain</title>
      <link>/research/2/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Feb 2007 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/research/2/</guid>
      <description>This paper shows that the United Kingdom since 1975 has exhibited a pattern of job polarization with rises in employment shares in the highest- and lowest-wage occupations. It argues that this is not entirely consistent with the idea of skill-biased technical change as a hypothesis about the impact of technology on the labor market. Instead, it shows that the “routinization” hypothesis recently proposed by Autor, Levy, and Murnane (2003) is a better explanation of job polarization.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Location</title>
      <link>/location/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/location/</guid>
      <description>My mailing and office addresses at Utrecht University.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Office Hours</title>
      <link>/officehours/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/officehours/</guid>
      <description>Schedule and location for my office hours at Utrecht University.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
